Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
计算机程序的构造和解释
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
翻译&&时间轴
杨启钊（windfarer）
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
赋值、状态和副作用
PROFESSOR: Well, so far we've invented enough programming
教授：到目前为止 我们已经教了很多编程技巧
to do some very complicated things.
来编写复杂程序了
And you surely learned a lot about programming at this point.
并且 到目前为止 关于编程你们学到了很多
You've learned almost all the most important tricks
你们已经学习了几乎所有的
that usually don't get taught to people until they have had a lot of experience.
那些拥有大量经验的人 才能领悟的技巧
For example, data directed programming is a major trick,
例如 数据导向编程就是一个主要的技巧
and yesterday you also saw an interpreted language.
昨天 你们也学习了一种解释型语言
We did this all in a computer language,
我们所做的这一切
at this point,
目前来讲
where there was no assignment statement.
都是在一种没有赋值语句的计算机语言中完成的
And presumably, for those of you who've seen your Basic or Pascal or whatever,
对于你们中用过Basic或者Pascal的人
that's usually considered the most important thing.
可能会认为“赋值”是最重要的东西
Well today, we're going to do something horrible.
今天我们将要做一些糟糕的事情
We're going to add an assignment statement.
我们要把赋值语句加进来
And since we can do all these wonderful things without it,
既然在没有赋值语句的时候 我们都可以很好地完成工作
why should we add it?
为什么我们还要把它加进来呢？
An important thing to understand it
为了理解它
is that today we're going to first of all, have a rule,
我们今天首先要定下一个规则
which is going to always be obeyed,
而我们将一直遵守这个规则
which is the only reason we ever add a feature to our language
这是我们为语言引入新的特性的唯一原因
is because there is a good reason.
是因为我们有一个好的理由
And the good reason is going to boil down to the ability,
好的理由归结为能力
you now get an ability to break a problem into pieces that are different sets of pieces
你现在获得了把问题分解为不同部分的能力
then you could have broken it down without that,
在没有相关能力之前可不行
give you another means of decomposition.
这让你有用来分解问题的另外方法
However, let's just start.
我们这就开始
Let me quick begin by reviewing
从回顾我们的
the kind of language that we have now.
现在已经有的这种语言出发
We've been writing what's called functional programs.
我们之前写的是所谓的函数式程序
And functional programs
函数式程序
are a kind of encoding of mathematical truths.
是一种对数学事实的编码
For example, when we look at
例如 当我们看到
the factorial procedure that you see on the slide here,
像幻灯片上这样阶乘过程时
it's basically two clauses.
基本上是两个子句
If n is one, the result is one,
如果n是1 则结果是1
otherwise n times factorial n minus one.
否则返回n乘以n-1的阶乘
That's factorial of n.
这是n的阶乘
Well, that is factorial of n.
它就是阶乘函数
And written down in some other obscure notation
如果用一些其他的记号
that you might have learned in calculus classes,
那些你在微积分课堂上学到的晦涩的符号来写
Ahh.. mathematical logic,
用数理逻辑来写
what you see there is if n equals one,
如果n等于1
for the result of n factorial is one, otherwise,
那么n的阶乘结果是1 否则
greater than one, n factorial is n times n minus one factorial.
如果n大于1 则n的阶乘就是n * (n-1)!
True statements,
数学事实
that's the kind of language we've been using.
就是我们一直使用的那种语言
And whenever we have true statements of that sort,
无论何时 我们遇到了这样的数学事实
there is a kind of, a way of understanding how they work
有一种理解它们工作原理的方法
which is that such processes can be evolved by substitution.
就是这些过程可以由代换演算而来
And so we see on the second slide here,
来看第二张幻灯片
that the way we understand the execution
我们理解执行的过程
implied by those statements in arranged in that order,
隐含在表达式的顺序中
is that you do successive substitutions of arguments
也就是你不断地将实际参数
for formal parameters in the body of a procedure.
代换到程序体的形式参数中
This is basically a sequence of equalities.
这些基本上是一系列的等价代换
Factorial four is four times factorial three.
4的阶乘是4乘以3的阶乘
That is four times three times factorial of two
也就是4乘以3乘以2的阶乘
and so on.
以此类推
We're always preserving truth.
我们总是保持数学事实成立
Even though we're talking about true statements,
尽管我们正在讨论数学事实
there might be more than one organization of these true statements
可能有多种数学事实的组织方式
to describe the computation of a particular function,
用来描述一个特定的函数的计算
the computation of the value of a particular function.
这个特定的函数的值的计算
So, for example, looking at the next one here.
所以 让我来看下这里的例子
Here is a way of looking at the sum of n and m.
这有一个计算m与n之和的方法
And we did this one by a recursive process.
我们使用一个递归的过程来完成
It's the increment of the sum of the decrement of n and m.
也就是(1+ (+ (-1+ n) m))
And, of course, there is some piece of mathematical logic here that describes that.
当然 这里也有相应的数理逻辑 解释了这个方法
It's the increment of the sum of the decrement of n and m,
也就是((n-1)+m)+1
just like that.
跟之前那个一样
So there's nothing particularly magic about that.
所以这儿并没有什么特殊的魔法
And, of course, if we can also look at an iterative process for the same,
当然 如果我们可以再来看一个相同的迭代过程
a program that evolves an iterative process, for the same function.
计算同样的函数 但是进行逐步迭代的程序
These are two things that compute the same answer.
这两个程序将得到同样的结果
And we have equivalent mathematical truths that are arranged there.
我们就可以认为这两个程序在数学上是等效的
And just the way you arrange those truths determine the particular process.
你对这些数学事实的排序 决定了具体（计算）过程
In the way choose and arrange them determines the process that's evolved.
我们对于这些数学事实的排序和选择 决定了过程发展的方式
So we have the flexibility of talking about both the function to be computed,
因此我们可以灵活地讨论待计算的函数
and the method by which it's computed.
以及计算该函数的所用的方法
So it's not clear we need more.
这并不清晰 我们需要再深入一些
However, today I'm going to this awful thing.
然而 今天我要来讲这个糟糕的东西
I'm going to introduce this assignment operation.
我要给大家介绍赋值操作
Now, what is this?
这是什么？
Well, first of all, there is going to be another kind of kind of statement, if you will,
首先 在编程语言中有另一种语句
in a programming language called Set!
这种语句叫做SET!
And SET! -- Things that do things like assignment,
具有赋值操作的语句
I'm going to put exclamation points after.
我都会在后面加上一个感叹号
We'll talk about what that means in a second.
这个感叹号代表什么意思呢？
The exclamation point, again like question mark,
这个感叹号 与问号类似
is an arbitrary thing we attach to the symbol which is the name,
是我们给名字随意加的符号
has no significance to the system.
它对于系统来说没有意义
The only significance is to me and you
它唯一的意义就是告诉我们
to alert you that this is an assignment of some sort.
注意这里是某种赋值操作
But we're going to set a variable to a value.
但是我们要给某个变量赋一个值
And what that's going to mean
这意味着
is that there is a time at which something happens.
在某个时间点发生了一些事情
Here's a time.
这是一个时间点
If I have time going this way,
如果时间以这个方向流动
it's a time axis.
这是个时间轴
Time progresses by walking down the page.
时间在平面上由上到下地流逝
Then an assignment is the first thing we have
赋值是第一个
that produces the difference between a before and an after.
使过去和未来之间产生差别的事物
All the other programs that we've written,
我们之前写的所有程序
that have no assignments in them,
都不包含赋值
the order in which they were evaluated didn't matter.
这些程序以怎样的顺序进行执行都没关系
But assignment is special,
但是赋值比较特殊
it produces a moment in time.
它使时间中产生了一个时间点
So there is a moment before the set occurs and after,
因此在SET!出现之前和之后中间有一个时间点
such that after this moment in time,
使得在这个时间点之后
the variable has the value, value.
变量有了一个值 即VALUE
Independent of what value it had before,
与这个变量之前的值无关
set! changes the value of the variable.
SET!改变了它的值
Until this moment,
在此之前
we had nothing that changed.
什么都没有发生改变
So, for example,
举例来说
one of the things we can think of
我们可以想到的一件事是
is that the procedures we write for something like factorial
我们写的一些过程 比如阶乘的程序
are in fact pretty much identical to the function factorial.
事实上与数学中的阶乘函数完全相同
Factorial of four, if I write fact4,
比如说4的阶乘 如果我写FACT(4)
independent of what context it's in,
无论它的上下文是怎样的
and independent of how many times I write it,
无论我写几遍
I always get the same answer.
我总能得到同样的结果
It's always 24.
结果永远是24
It's a unique map from the argument to the answer.
它是参数到到结果的唯一映射
And all the programs we've written so far are like that.
迄今为止 我们之前写的所有程序都是这样的
However, once I have assignment, that isn't true.
然而 当引入赋值后 一切就不同了
So, for example,
举个例子
if I were to define count to be one.
如果我将COUNT定义为1
And then I'm going to define also a procedure,
然后定义一个过程
a simple procedure called demo,
一个叫做DEMO的简单过程
which takes argument x and does the following operations.
它接受参数X 并执行下面的操作
It first sets x to x plus one.
首先将X修改为X+1
My gosh, this looksjust like FORTRAN, right--
我的天啊！ 这看起来就像FORTRAN是吧？
in a funny syntax.
只是用了些有趣的语法
And then add to x count,
然后返回(+ X COUNT)
Oh, I just made a mistake.
哦 我刚犯了个错
I want to say,
我的意思是
set! count to one plus count.
(SET! COUNT (1+ COUNT))
It's this thing defined here.
就是我在这里定义的这个
And then add and said plus x count.
然后X和COUNT相加
Then I can try this procedure.
然后就可以试着运行这个过程了
Let's run it.
让我们运行它
So, suppose I get a prompt and I say,
假设我可以输入
demo 3
输入(DEMO 3)
Well, what happens here?
这里发生了什么？
The first thing that happens
发生的第一件事情是
is count is currently one.
COUNT现在是1
Currently, there is a time.
现在 这是一个时间点
We're talking about time.
我们在讨论时间点
x gets three.
X的值为3
At this moment,
在这个时刻
I say, oh yes, count is incremented, so count is two.
COUNT增加了 所以COUNT是2
two plus three is five.
2加3等于5
So the answer I get out is five.
所以结果是5
Then I say, demo of say, three again.
然后我再一次 输入(DEMO 3)
Okay, What do I get?
结果是什么？
Well, now count is two, it's not one anymore,
现在COUNT是2 它不再是1了
because I have incremented it.
因为我让COUNT加1了
But now I go through this process,
但现在我执行这个过程
three goes into x,
X的值为3
count becomes one plus count, so that's three now.
COUNT变为1+COUNT 因此现在是3了
The sum of those two is six,
这两个相加是6
so the answer is six.
所以结果是6
And what we see
我们可以发现
is the same expression
同样的表达式
leads to two different answers,
因为时间节点的不同
depending upon time.
得到了不同的结果
So demo is not a function,
所以DEMO不是函数
does not compute a mathematical function.
或者说它并没有计算一个数学意义上的函数
In fact, you could also see why now, of course,
事实上 你可以知道这是为什么
this is the first place where the substitution model isn't going to work.
因为这里是第一处代换模型失效的地方
This kills the substitution model dead.
它给代换模型判了死刑
You know, with quotation there were some little problems
有些关于引用的一些小问题
that a philosopher might notice with substitutions,
哲学家可能注意到 特别是与代换有关时
because you have to worry about what deductions you can make
因为当你在引用中进行代换时
when you substitute into quotes,
需要考虑你可以得到什么样的推论
if you're allowed to do that at all.
如果你能够使用代换的话
But
但是
here the substitution model is dead,
在这里代换模型已经失效了
can't do anything at all.
它什么也不能做了
Because,
因为
Supposing I wanted to use a substitution model to consider substituting for count?
假设我想用代换模型来考虑COUNT的代换
Well, my gosh, if I substitute for here and here,
如果我在这里和这里进行代换
they're different ones.
它们是不同的
It's not the same count any more.
它不再是同一个COUNT了
I get the wrong answer.
我得到了错误的结果
The substitution model is a static phenomenon
代换模型是一个静态的现象
describes things that are true
它描述的事实
and not things that change.
而不是变动
Here, we have truths that change.
这里 我们的事实变动了
OK, Well, before I give you any understanding of this,
那么 在我给出任何解释之前
this is very bad.
这很糟糕
Now, we've lost our model of computation.
我们失去了我们的计算模型
And,
并且
pretty soon, I'm going to have to build you a new model of computation.
很快 我将不得不构建一个新的计算模型
But ours plays with this, just now, in an informal sense.
我们现在的讨论 还是从一个不严谨的角度进行的
Of course, what you already see
当然 你们已经看到的是
is that when I have something like assignment,
当我做一些像赋值之类的事情时
the model that we're going to need
我们所需要的模型
is different from the model that we had before
与我们之前模型不同
in that, the variables, those symbols like count, or x
在这个的模型中 像COUNT或X这样的符号
are no longer going to refer to the values they have,
不再关联于它们的值
but rather to some sort of place where the value restored.
而是关联于某个储存这些值的地方
We're going to have to think that way for a while.
我们将花些时间来适应这种思想
And it's going to be a very bad thing
这将是一个很糟糕的事情
and cause a lot of trouble.
并且会造成很多麻烦
And so, as I said, the very fact that we're inventing this bad thing,
所以 就像我说的 若非理由周全
means that there had better be a good reason for it,
不然绝不要发明这种糟糕的东西
otherwise, just a waste of time and a lot of effort.
否则 就是劳神费力
Let's just look at some of it just to play.
让我们看看一些可以讨论的东西
Supposing we write down the functional version,
假设我们写了函数式版本的阶乘函数
functional meaning in the old style,
我们以前的就是“函数式”风格
of factorial by an iterative process.
具有迭代计算过程的阶乘函数
Factorial of n.
N的阶乘
we're going to iterate of m and i,
我们要(ITER M I)
which says if i is greater than n,
就是说如果I大于N
then the result is m,
则结果是M
otherwise,
否则
the result of iterating the product of i and m.
结果是(ITER (* I M))
So m is going to be the product that I'm accumulating.
所以M将是我累积的结果
m is the product.
M就是这个乘积[注：此处教授笔误]
And the count I'm going to increase by one.
然后我要把COUNT加1
Plus, ITER, ELSE, COND, define.
（闭合括号中）
I'm going to start this up.
我在这里启动这个内部过程
And these days, you should have no trouble reading something like this.
对于这种代码 我想大家早已驾轻就熟了
What I have here is a product there being accumulated and a counter.
这里是一个累积的乘积 和一个计数器
I start them up both at one.
我让它们都从1开始
I'm going to buzz the counter up,
我将不断让计数器增加
i goes to i plus one every time around.
每一轮I变成I+1
But that's only way our putting a time on the process,
这是我们在这个过程中设置时间的唯一方法
each of this is just a set of truths,
这些都是一系列的事实
true rules.
真实的规则
And m is going to get a new values of i and m,
M将获得一个新的值 就是I乘M
i times m each time around,
每一轮I乘以M
and eventually i is going to be bigger than n,
最终I将大于N
in which case, the answer's going to be m.
在这种情况下 结果就是M
Now, I'm speaking to you, use time in this.
我给你们讲课的时候 用到了“时间”这个概念
That's just because I know how the computer works.
那是因为我知道计算机是怎么工作的
But I didn't have to.
但是我没必要这么做
This could be a purely mathematical description at this point,
这完全可以有一个纯数学的解释
because substitution will work for this.
因为在这里代换可以工作
But let's set right down a similar sort of program,
但是我们写一个类似的程序
using the same algorithm,
使用相同的算法
but with assignments.
但使用了赋值
So this is called the functional version.
所以这个叫做函数式版本
I want to write down an imperative version.
我想写个命令式的版本的
Factorial of n.
N的阶乘
I'm going to create my two variables.
我要创建两个变量
Let i initialize itself to one,
把I的值初始化为1
and m be initialized to one, similar.
M也初始化为1
We'll create a loop
我们创建一个循环
which has COND greater than i, and if i is greater than n, we're done.
如果I比N大 循环结束
And the result is m,
结果是M
the product I'm accumulating.
也就是我累积的乘积
Otherwise,
否则
I'm going to write down three things to do.
我接下来要做三件事
I'm going to set! m to the product of i and m,
我要把M赋值为I*M
set! i to the sum of i and one,
把I赋值为I+1
and go around the loop again.
然后继续循环
Looks very familiar to you FORTRAN programmers.
你们中的FORTRAN程序员应该觉得眼熟
ELSE, COND, define,
（闭合括号中）
funny syntax though.
就是这种语法有点陌生
Start the loop up,
启动循环
and that's the program.
程序就写完了
Now, this program,
那么 这个程序
how do we think about it?
我们应该怎么思考它呢？
Well, let's just say what we're seeing here.
先来看看这里是什么
There are two local variables, i and m,
这里有两个局部变量 I和M
that have been initialized to one.
它们都被初始化为1
Every time around the loop, I test to see if i is greater than n,
在每一次循环里 我检测I是否大于N
which is the input argument,
就是我们传入的参数
and if so, the result is the product being accumulated in m.
如果成立的话 结果就是M中所累积的乘积
However, if it's not the end of the loop,
然而 如果循环没有结束
if I'm not done,
如果我们的工作没有结束
then what I'm going to do is change the product
则我们要把乘积
to be the result of multiplying i times the current product.
变为i与当前乘积的结果
Which is sort of what we were doing here.
就是我们在这里做过的事情
Except here I wasn't changing.
除了这里我没有改动
I was making another copy,
我创建了一个复本
because the substitution model says, you copy the body of the procedure
因为代换模型就是你复制过程的体
with the arguments substituted for the formal parameters.
并用实际参数代换形式参数
Here I'm not worried about copying,
这里 我考虑的不是副本
here I've changed the value of m.
在这里 我已经改变了M的值
I also then change the value of i to i plus one,
我也把I的值变成了I+1
and go buzzing around.
然后继续循环
Seems like essentially the same program,
看起来是一样的程序
but there are some ways of making errors here
在今天引入赋值之后
that didn't exist until today.
我们在这里有很多种方式犯错
For example,
例如
if I were to do the horrible thing
如果我在赋值的时候
of not being careful in writing my program
没有小心地写程序
and interchange those two assignments,
把两个赋值的顺序调换了
the program wouldn't compute the same function.
程序计算的就不是相同的函数了
I get a timing error because there's a dependency
我得到了一个时间错误 因为这儿有个依赖关系
that m depends upon having the last value of i.
因为M依赖于I上一次的值
If I try change i first,
如果我先改变I的值
then I've got the wrong value of i when I multiply by m.
就会在乘以M的时候 得到错误的I值
It's a bug that wasn't available until this moment,
没有赋值的话不会存在这样的BUG
until we introduced something that had time in it.
这是由于我们引入了某些包含时间的东西造成的
So, as I said,
如我所说的
first we need a new model of computation,
首先 我们需要一个新的计算模型
and second, we have to be damn good reason for doing this kind of ugly thing.
然后 需要有一个非常好的理由来支持我们做如此丑陋的事
Are there any questions?
有什么问题吗？
Speak loudly, David
David 大点儿声说
AUDIENCE: I'm confused about, we've introduced set now,
学生：现在 我们引入了SET!
but we had let before and define before.
但是之前我们已经有LET和DEFINE了
I'm confused about the difference between the three.
我不太清楚它们的区别
Wouldn't define work in the same situation as set!
DEFINE不能像SET!一样用吗？
if you introduced it a bit?
请详细讲讲
PROFESSOR: No, define is intended for setting something once the first time,
教授：不 DEFINE用于创建并初始化
for making it, OK?
为了创建它
You've never seen me write on a blackboard
你永远也不会见到我在黑板上
two defines in a row
在同一行写两个DEFINE
whose intention was to change the old value of some variable to a new one.
只是为了让某个变量的旧值变成一个新的值
AUDIENCE: Is that by convention or--
学生：这是一个约定俗成的规矩 还是--
PROFESSOR: No, it's intention.
教授：不 这是有意为之的
Okay? The answer is,
答案是
that, for example,
举个例子
internal to a procedure,
在一个过程内部
two defines in a row are illegal,
两个DEFINE写在一行里是非法的
two defines in a row of the same variable.
对于同一个变量DEFINE两次是非法的
x can't be defined twice.
X不能被DEFINE两次
Whether or not a system catches that error is a different question,
而系统会不会捕获这个错误 就是另一个问题了
but I legislate to you
但是我定下规矩
that define happens once on anything.
任何东西都只能DEFINE一次
Now, indeed, in interactive debugging,
确实 在交互式调试中
we intend that you interacting with your computer will redefine things,
我们打算让你与计算机交互时可以重新DEFINE一些东西
and so there's a special exception made for interactive debugging.
所以交互式调试时产生的是一个特殊的异常
But define is intended to mean to set up something
但是DEFINE的意思是建立某些东西
which will be forever that value after that point.
在那个时间点后 它的值是永远不变的
It's as if all the defines were done at the beginning.
好像所有的DEFINE都是在最开始完成的
In fact, the only legal place to put a define in Scheme internal to a procedure
事实上 在Scheme过程中 DEFINE的唯一合法使用地方
is just at the beginning of a lambda expression,
就是在LAMBDA表达式的开始
which is the beginning of the body of a procedure.
也就是过程体的开始
Now, let of course does nothing like either of that.
LET当然与那个不一样
I mean, if you look at what's happening with a let,
如果你想知道LET发生了什么
this happens again exactly once.
LET只会绑定一次
It sets up a context where i and m are values one and one.
它建立了一个I和M的值分别为1的上下文
That context exists throughout this scope,
这个上下文存在于整个作用域中
this region of the program.
也就是这个程序范围
However, you don't think of that let as setting i again.
然而 你不会认为LET再次设置了I的值
It doesn't change it.
它没有改变I的值
i never changes because of the let.
因为LET的作用 I将永远不会变化
i gets created because of let.
因为LET的作用 I才被创建
In fact,
实际上
the let is a very simple idea.
LET是一个非常简单的想法
Let does nothing more,
LET不会做别的事情
Let a variable one to have value one
LET的语义是……
I'll write this down a little bit more neatly;
我把它写得更准确点
Let's write, var one have value, the value of expression e1,
表达式 (var1 e1)
and variable two, have this value of the expression e2,
还有(var2 e2)
in an expression e3,
在表达式e3中
is the same thing as a procedure of var one and var two, the formal parameters,
与一个以var1和var2为形式参数的过程一样
and e3 being the body,
e3成为过程的体
where var one is bound to the value of e1,
在这里 var1与e1的值绑定
and var two gets the value of e2.
var2与e2的值绑定
So this is, in fact, a perfectly understandable thing from a substitution point of view.
所以实际上 这是一个从代换的角度来看很容易理解的东西
This is really the same expression written in two different ways.
其实就是同一个表达式的两种不同的写法
In fact, the way the actual system works
事实上 系统真正的工作方式
is this gets translated into this before anything happens.
就是在运行之前把代码翻译成这种形式
AUDIENCE: OK, I'm still unclear as then what makes the difference between a let and a define. They could--
学生：我还是不清楚是什么造成了LET和DEFINE之间的区别
PROFESSOR: A define is a syntactic sugar,
教授：DEFINE就是个语法糖
whereby, essentially a bunch of variables get created by lets and then set up once.
本质上来说 是通过LET创建一系列变量 然后给它们一次性赋值
OK, time for the first break, I think. Thank you.
好吧 我们休息一会
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
赋值、状态和副作用
Well let's see.
看
I now have to rebuild the model of computation,
现在 我不得不重建计算模型
so you understand how some such mechanical mechanism could work
使得你能够明白那些机制是如何运作的
that can do what we've just talked about.
来完成我们刚才说的那些工作
I just recently destroyed your substitution model.
我刚刚摧毁了你们的代换模型
Unfortunately, this model is significantly more complicated than the substitution model.
不幸的是 这个模型比代换模型要复杂得多
It's called the environment model.
这个模型叫环境模型
And I'm going to have to introduce some terminology,
我即将介绍一些术语
which is very good terminology for you to know anyway.
无论如何 你知道这些术语都是很好的
It's about names.
它是关于名字的
And we're going to give names to the kinds of names things have
我们要给事物的各种名字
and the way those names are used.
和名字的使用途径以名字
So this is a meta-description, if you will.
如果硬要说的话 这是一个元描述
Anyway, there is a pile of an unfortunate terminology here,
总之 这里面有一堆糟糕的术语
but we're going to need this to understand what's called the environment model.
但我们需要利用它们来理解所谓的“环境模型”
We're about to do a little bit of boring, dog-work here.
我们可能要做一点无聊的事情了
Let's look at the first transparency.
我们来看第一张张幻灯片
And we see a description of a word called bound.
我们看到了术语“约束”的解释
And we're going to say that a variable, v,
我们会说一个变量V
is bound in an expression, e,
被约束在表达式E中
if the meaning of e is unchanged by the uniform replacement of a variable w,
如果用一个没有出现在E中的变量W 对变量V统一换名
not occurrent if for every occurrence of v in e.
表达式语义没有发生改变
Now that's a long sentence,
这个解释很长
so, I think, I'm going to have to say a little bit about that
在我们在被搞糊涂之前
before we even fool around at all here.
我应该再多解释下
Bound variables we're talking about here.
我们这里讨论的约束变量
And you've seen lots of them.
你们已经看到它们很多次了
You may not know that you've seen lots of them.
只是你们可能还没意识到
Well, I suppose in your logic, you saw a logical variables like,
在逻辑学中 你们看到一个逻辑变量
for every x there exists a y such that p is true of x and y from your calculus class.
就像微积分课上的 对于任意任何X 存在一个Y 使得P为真
This variable, x, and this variable, y, are bound,
这个变量X 这个变量Y 它们是约束变量
because,
因为
the meaning of this expression
这个表达式的含义
does not depend upon the particular letters I used to describe x and y.
不取决于我用来描述X和Y的具体字母
If I were to change the w for x,
如果我用W替换X
then said for every w there exists a y such that p is true of w and y,
则可以说对于任意W 存在一个Y使得P为真
it would be the same sentence.
它们其实是同一句话
That's what it means.
就是这个意思
Or another case of this that you've seen is integral say,
又或者说 你们看到这样一个积分
from 0 to one of dx over one plus x square.
对dx/(1+x^2)从0到1积分
Well that's something you see all the time.
这就是你们经常见到的那种东西
And this x is a bound variable.
这个x是一个约束变量
If I change that to a t,
如果我把它换成t
the expression is still the same thing.
这个表达式其实没有变化
This is a 1/4 of the arctan of one or something here, something like that.
就是arctan(1)/4之类的
Yes, that's the arctan of one.
是的 就是arctan(1)
So bound variables are actually fairly common,
所以约束变量事实上很常见
for those of you who have played a bit with mathematics.
如果你们接触过一些数学的话
Well, let's go into the programming world.
好 让我们来到编程的世界
Instead of the quantifier being something like,
现在量词不再是
for every, or there exists, or integral,
所有、存在和积分
a quantifier is a symbol that binds a variable.
我们有一个符号作为量词 用于约束变量
And we are going to use the quantifier lambda
我们要使用量词LAMBDA
as being the essential thing that binds variables.
作为约束变量的一个必要的东西
And so we have some nice examples here
我们有一个极好的例子
like that procedure of one argument y which does the following thing.
对于以Y为参数的过程 做了以下的事情
It calls the procedure of one argument x,
它调用一个含单个参数X的过程
which multiplies x by y,
该过程 将X乘以Y
and applies that to three.
并应用于3
That procedure has the property there of two bound variables in it,
这个过程中包含两个约束变量
x and y
X和Y
This quantifier, lambda here, binds this y,
这个LAMBDA量词 约束了这个Y
and this quantifier, lambda, binds that x.
这个LAMBDA量词 约束了这个X
Because, if I were to take an arbitrary symbol does not occur in this expression like w
因为 如果我用了一个没有出现在表达式中的任意符号 如W
and replace all y's with w's in this expression,
用W替换表达式中的所有Y
the expression is still the same,
这个表达式仍与原来的相同
the same procedure.
是相同的过程
And this is an important idea.
这是一个重要的想法
The reason why we had such things like that
我们有这种东西的原因
is a kind of modularity.
这是一种模块性
If two people are writing programs,
如果有两个人写程序
and they work together,
并且他们在合作编程
it shouldn't matter what names they use internal to their own little machines that they're building.
在他们自己构建的小项目里用什么命名都没有关系
And so, what I'm really telling you there,
所以 实际上我想告诉你们
is that, for example,
例如
this is equivalent to that procedure of one argument y which
这个表达式等于 以Y为参数的过程
uses that procedure of one argument z which multiplies z by y.
使用这个对于一个参数Z的过程 这个过程将Z乘以Y
Because nobody cares what I used in here.
因为没人关心我在这用什么
It's a nice example.
这是一个极好的例子
On the other hand,
另一方面
I have some variables that are not bound.
我有一些未被约束的变量
And example,
举个例子
that procedure of one argument x
这个对于一个以X为参数的过程
which multiplies x by y
将X乘以Y
In this case,
在这个例子中
y is not bound.
y没有被约束
Supposing y had the value three,
假设Y的值是3
and z had the value four,
Z的值是4
then this procedure would be the thing that multiplies its argument by three.
那么这个过程就是把它的参数乘以3
If I were to replace every instance of y with z,
如果我把所有的y都用z来代替
I would have a different procedure which multiplies every argument that's given by four.
我将得到一个完全不同的过程 它会把参数乘以4
And, in fact, we have a name for such a variable.
事实上 我们给这类变量取了个名字
Here, we say that a variable, v, is free in the expression, e,
我们把表达式E中的变量V叫做自由变量
if the meaning of the expression, e, is changed by the uniform replacement of a variable, w, not occurring in e,
如果用没有出现在E中的变量W统一替换E中所有的V
for every occurrence of v and e.
使得表达式E的含义发生了改变
So,
所以
So that's why this variable over here, y, is a free variable.
所以这就是为什么这个变量Y 是一个自由变量
And so free variables in this expression--
所以 这个表达式里的自由变量
And other examples of that is that
另一个例子是
is that procedure of one argument y,
对于一个以Y为参数的过程
which is just what we had before,
就像我们之前的那个一样
which uses that procedure of one argument x
调用以X为参数的过程
that multiplies x by y--
将X与Y相乘--
use that on three.
并应用于3
This procedure has a free variable in it
这个过程中有一个自由变量
which is asterisk.
也就是这个星号
See, because,
因为
if that has a normal meaning of multiplication,
如果它表示正常意义的乘法
then if I were to replace uniformly all asterisks with pluses,
如果我统一地用加号来代替星号
then the meaning of this expression would change.
这个表达式的含义就变了
That's what you mean by a free variable.
这就是自由变量的意思
So, so far you've learned some logician words
现在 你们已经学到了一些逻辑学术语
which describe the way names are used.
用它们可以解释名字的用法
Now, we have to do a little bit more playing around here,
我们要需要更进一步深入
a little bit more.
再多了解一些
I want to tell you about
我想给你们讲讲
about the regions are over which variables are defined.
变量被定义的区域
You see,
你瞧
we've been very informal about this up till now,
目前为止 我们已经相当不正式了
and, of course, many of you have probably understood very clearly or most of you,
当然 你们中的一些 或者大部分人可能已经理解得很透彻了
that the x that's being declared here
在这里被声明的X
is defined only in here.
只被定义在这里
This x is the defined only in here,
这个X 只被定义在这里
and this y is defined only in here.
这个Y 只被定义在这里
We have a name for such an idea. It's called a scope.
我们给这个概念取了个名字 叫“作用域”
And let me give you another piece of terminology.
我给你们再讲个术语
It's a long story.
这个就比较复杂
If x is a bound variable in e,
如果X是E中的一个约束变量
then there is a lambda expression where it is bound.
那么它是约束于一个LAMBDA表达式中
So the only way you can get a bound variable ultimately is by lambda expression.
LAMBDA表达式是约束变量的唯一方式
Then you may worry,
你可能会担心
does define quite an exception to this?
DEFINE是它的一个例外吗？
And it turns out, we could always arrange things so you don't need any defines.
事实证明 通过巧妙安排 我们可以避免使用DEFINE
And we'll see that in a while.
一会我们就能看到了
It's a very magical thing.
它一个非常神奇的东西
So define really can go away.
所以我们完全不需要DEFINE
The really, only thing that makes names is lambda .
实际上 唯一能创建名字的东西是LAMBDA
That's its job.
这就是它的职责
And what's so amazing about a lot of things
多么的令人惊奇
is you can compute with only lambda.
很多东西你只凭借LAMBDA就可以计算
But, in any case,
但是 在任何情况下
a lambda expression has a place where it declares a variable.
一个LAMBDA表达式有一个地方来声明变量
We call it the formal parameter list
我们把它称为形式参数表
and we say or the bound variable list.
或者叫 约束变量表
We say that the lambda expression binds -- so it's a verb
我们说LAMBDA表达式约束了--这是一个动词
--binds the variables declared in it's bound variable list.
--约束了在约束变量表里声明的变量
In addition, those parts of the expression where the variable is defined,
另外 表达式中定义变量的那些部分
which was declared by some declaration
是被一些声明所声明的
is called the scope of that variable.
这些部分被叫做变量的作用域
So these are scopes.
所以 这些是作用域
This is the scope of y.
这是Y的作用域
And this is the scope of x--
这是X的作用域--
that sort of thing.
以此类推
OK,
好
well, now we have enough terminology
现在我们有了足够多的术语
to begin to understand how to make a new model for computation
可以开始理解如何建立一个新的计算模型了
because the key thing going on here
因为 这里很重要的一点是
is that we destroyed the substitution model,
我们摧毁了代换模型
and we now have to have a model
我们现在不得不需要一个模型
that represents the names as referring to places.
来体现表示名字被关联到某些地方
Because if we are going to change something,
因为 如果我们要改变某个东西
then we have a place where it's stored.
我们就需要一个存它的地方
You see,
请想一想
if a name only refers to a value,
如果一个名字只是关联于一个值
and if I tried to change the name's meaning,
如果我试图改变这个名字的含义
well, that's not clear.
这不怎么明确
There's nothing that is the place that that name referred to.
因为没有名字可以关联的地方
How am I really saying it?
该怎么解释呢……
There're nothing shared among all of the instances of that name.
也就是名字的所有实例之间没有共享任何东西
And what we really mean, by a name,
也就是说 对于一个名字
is that we find something out.
是用来让我们找到某些东西的
We've given something a name, and you have it,
我们把名字给某个东西 然后你拿到了它
and you have it, because I'm given you a reference to it,
你能得到它 是因为我给了你一个它的引用
and I've given you a reference to it.
我把对它的引用给了你
And we'll see a lot about that.
我们会看到很多相关的例子
So let me tell you about environments.
让我们继续学习“环境”
I need the overhead projection machine,
我需要用一下头顶上的投影仪
thank you.
谢谢你
And so here
这里
is a bunch of environment structures.
是一堆环境结构
An environment is a way of doing substitutions virtually.
环境就是执行虚拟的代换的一种方法
It represents a place
它代表了一个地方
where something is stored which is the substitutions that you haven't done.
是存储你的未完成的代换的地方
It's a place where everything accumulates,
它是一个积累各种东西的地方
where the names of the variables are associated with the values they have
在那里 变量的名字与值关联在一起
such that,
使得
when you say, what dose this name mean,
当你问某个名字是什么意思的时候
you look it up in an environment.
你要在一个环境中寻找答案
So an environment is a function,
所以环境是一个函数
or a table,
或一张表
or something like that.
或类似的东西
But it's a structured sort of table.
但它是一种结构化的表
It's made out of things called frames.
它是由框架构成
Frames are pieces of environment,
框架是环境的一部分
and they are chained together,
它们被链接在一起
in some nice ways,
以某种很好的方式
by what's called parent links or something like that.
用一种叫做父链接之类的东西
So here,
这里
we have an environment structure
有一个环境结构
consisting of three environments, basically, A, B, and C.
它由三个环境组成 分别是A B和C
d is also an environment, but it's the same one,
D也是环境 但它和C是一样的
they share.
它们共享了同一个环境
And that's the essence of assignment.
那就是赋值的本质所在
If I change a variable,
如果我改变了一个变量
a value of a valuable that lives here, like that one,
比如改变这个变量的值
it should be visible from all places that you're looking at it from.
那么它将在所有地方都可见
Take this one, x.
用x来举例
If I change the x to four,
如果我将X改为4
it's visible from other places.
在其他地方也是可见的
But I'm not going to worry about that right now.
但是我们现在不去关心这个
We're going to talk a lot about that in a little while.
过一会儿会详细讨论这个问题
What do we have here?
这里有什么？
Well, these are called frames. Here is a frame,
这些叫做框架 这是一个框架
here's a frame
这是一个框架
and here's a frame.
这也是一个框架
A is an environment which consists of
A是一个环境
the table label which is frame two,
它由框架II
followed by the table labeled frame one.
和框架I组成
And, in this environment,
在这个环境中
in C, this environment, frame two,
在环境C中 在框架II中
uh....x and y are bound.
X和Y是被约束的
They have values.
它们具有值
Sorry, in frame one
对不起 是在框架I中
In frame two,
而在框架II中
z is bound,
Z被约束
and x is bound,
X被约束
and y is bound,
并且Y也是被约束的
but the value of x that we see,
但是我们看到的X的值
looking from this point of view,
从这个角度来看
is this x. It's x is seven,
是这个X 它的值是7
rather than this one which is three.
而不是这个值为3的X
We say that this x shadows this x.
我们称之为 这个X遮蔽了这个X
From environment three--
从环境III
from frame three,
从框架III
from environment b,
从环境B
which refers to frame three,
它引用了框架III
we have variables m and y bound and also x.
变量M和Y被约束 X也被约束
This y shadow this one.
这个Y遮蔽了这个Y
So the value, looking from this point of view,
从这个角度来看
of y is two.
Y的值是2
The value for looking from this point of view
从这个角度来看
and m is one. And the value, looking from this point of view, of x is three.
M的值是1 X的值是3
So there we have
所以 我们有了一个
a very simple environment structure made out of frames.
由框架构成的非常简单的环境结构
These correspond to the applications of procedures.
它们与过程的应用相一致
And we'll see that in a second.
我们马上就会看到
So now I have to make you some other nice little structure that we build.
现在要给你们看看我们构建的一些其他的很好的小结构
Next slide,
下一张幻灯片
we see an object,
我们可以看到一个对象
which I'm going to draw procedures.
我描绘的是一个过程的图像
This is a procedure.
这是一个过程
A procedure is made out of two parts.
过程由两个部分组成
It's sort of like a cons.
这有点像CONS
However, it's the two parts.
不管怎样 它有两个部分
The first part refers to some code,
第一个部分指向一些代码
something that can be executed,
这些代码将会被执行
a set of instructions, if you will. You can think of it that way.
你可以把它视作一组指令
And the second part is the environment.
第二部分是环境
The procedure is the whole thing.
这就是过程的全部了
And we're going to have to use this
我们要用它
to capture the values of the free variables that occur in the procedure.
来捕获出现在过程中的自由变量的值
If a variable occurs in the procedure
如果变量出现在过程中
it's either bound in that procedure or free.
它不是被约束的就是自由的
If it's bound,
如果它是被约束的
then the value will somehow be easy to find.
则它的值将很容易被找到
It will be in some easy environment to get at.
它将存在于某个很容易找到的环境中
If it's free,
如果它是自由的
we're going to have to have something that goes with the procedure
我们就必须在过程中放入一些东西
that says where we'll go look for its value.
用来指导我们查询自由变量的值
And the reasons why are not obvious yet,
相关理由目前还不清楚
but will be soon.
但很快就要真相大白了
So here's a procedure object. It's a composite object
这里有一个对象 它是个复合对象
consisting of a piece of code and a environment structure.
由一些代码和一个环境结构组成
Now I will tell you the new rules, the complete new rules,
现在我要告诉你们一些全新的规则
for evaluation.
关于执行的规则
The first rule is-- there's only two of them.
仅有的两条规则的第一条是--
These correspond to the substitution model rules.
这些规则与代换模型规则相对应
And the first one has to do with
第一条规则是用来解决
how do you apply a procedure to its arguments?
如何把一个过程 应用到参数上的问题
Okay, And a procedural object is applied to a set of arguments
程序对象被应用于一组参数
by constructing a new frame.
是通过构建一个新的框架来完成
That frame will contain the mapping of the former parameters to the actual parameters
那个框架将包含形式参数
of the arguments that were supplied in the call.
到调用中使用的实际参数的映射
As you know,
如你所知
when we make up a call to a procedure like lambda x times x y,
当我们调用一个过程 如(LAMBDA (X) (* X Y))
and we call that with the argument three,
然后我们以3为参数调用它
then we're going to need some mapping of x to three.
那么我们需要某个从X到3的映射
It's the same thing as later substituting, if you will
你可以把它想做是代换的一种
the three for the x in the old model.
在旧的模型中 用3代换X
So I'm going to build a frame which contains x equals three
所以我要建立一个框架
as the information in that frame.
在框架中包含X等于3的这个信息
Now,
现在
the body of the procedure will then have to be evaluated which is this,
过程的体即将被执行
and will be evaluated in an environment
它将在一个环境中执行
which is constructed by adjoining the new frame that we just made
这个环境是由我们创建的新框架邻接组合而成
to the environment which was part of the procedure that we applied.
它是我们所应用的过程的一部分
So I'm going to make a little example of that here.
所以 举个例子
Supposing I have some environment.
假设我有一些环境
Here's a frame which represents it.
画个方框代表它
And some procedure-- which I'm going to draw with circles here because it's easier than little triangles--
以及一些过程--我画圆来代表它们 因为这比小三角形好画--
Ummm.. sorry, those are rhombuses,
抱歉 是菱形
rhomboidal little pieces of fruit jelly or something.
小块菱形的果冻之类的东西
So here's a procedure which takes this environment.
这有一个使用这个环境的过程
And the procedure has a piece of code,
这个过程有一些代码
which is a lambda expression,
是一个LAMBDA表达式
which binds x and y
约束了X和Y
and then executes an expression, e.
然后执行了表达式E
And this is the procedure.
这个过程就是这样的
We'll call it p.
我们叫它P
I wish to apply that procedure to three and four.
我希望将这个过程应用于3和4
So I want to do p of three and four.
所以我在这写(P 3 4)
What I'm going to do, of course, is make a new frame.
我要做的事情则是 创建一个新的框架
I build a frame
创建一个框架
which contains x equals three,
框架中X等于3
and y equals four.
而Y等于4
I'm going to connect that frame
我要把这个框架
to this frame over here.
连接到这一个框架上
And then this environment,
对于这个环境
with I will call b,
我把它叫做B
is the environment in which I will evaluate the body of e.
我会在这个环境中求值E的体
Now,
现在
e may contain references to x and y and other things.
E可能包含了X和Y的引用以及一些别的东西
x and y will have values right here.
X和Y的值在这里
Other things will have their values here.
其他的变量的值在这里
How do we get this frame?
怎样才能获取这个框架呢？
That we do by the construction of procedures
我们通过过程构建来完成
which is the other rule.
这就是另一条规则了
And I think that's the next slide.
请看下一张幻灯片
Rule two,
规则二
when a lambda expression is evaluated,
当一个LAMBDA表达式被求值时
relative to a particular environment--
相对于某个特定的环境--
See,
例如
the way I get a procedure is by evaluating the lambda expression.
获取一个过程的方式就是求值一个LAMBDA表达式
Here's a lambda expression.
这里有一个LAMBDA表达式
By evaluating it,
通过对它求值
I get a procedure which I can apply to three.
我获得了一个可以应用于3的过程
Now this lambda expression
现在这个LAMBDA表达式
is evaluated in an environment where y is defined.
在一个Y已被定义的环境中执行
And I want the body of this which contains a free version of y.
我希望这个过程的体中包括的Y是自由的
y is free in here,
在这里面 Y是自由的
it's bound over the whole thing,
但是在整个的表达式中却是被约束的
but it's free over here.
而在这里是自由的
I want that y to be this one.
我想让这两个Y指称同一个Y
I evaluate this body of this procedure in the environment where y was created.
我在Y被创建的环境中求值这个过程的体
That's this kind of thing, because that was done by application.
就像这个一样 因为那是通过应用完成的
Now,
现在
if I ever want to look up the value of y,
如果我还想查找Y的值
I have to know where it is.
我就必须知道它在哪
Therefore, this procedural was created,
因此 这个过程在被创建时
the creation of the procedure which is the result of evaluating that lambda expression
过程的创建 也就是对LAMBDA表达式求值的结果
had better capture a pointer or remember the frame in which y was bound.
最好是获取一个指针或记住Y被约束在哪个框架中
So that's what this rule is telling us.
这就是这个规则的内容
So, for example,
那么 举个例子
if I happen to be evaluating a lambda expression,
如果我恰好求值了一个LAMBDA表达式
lambda expression in e,
在E中的LAMBDA表达式
lambda of say, x and y, let's call it g in e,
在E中求值(LAMBDA (X Y) G)
evaluating that.
对其求值
all that means is I now construct a procedure object.
这些事的意义就是我现在构建了一个过程对象
e is some environment.
E是某个环境
e is something which has a pointer to it.
有个指针指向E
I construct a procedure object that points up to that environment,
我构建了一个过程对象指向了这个环境
where the code of that
它的代码
is a lambda expression or whatever that translates into.
是一个LAMBDA表达式 或者是某种中间代码
And this is the procedure.
而这就是一个过程
So this produces for me-- this -- this
它为我生成了这个和这个
this object here,
这个对象
this environment pointer,
这个环境指针
captures the place where this lambda expression was evaluated,
获取了求值LAMBDA表达式时的环境
where the definition was used,
定义所使用的环境
where the definition was used to make a procedure,
创建一个过程时的定义所用的环境
to make the procedure.
从而创建了过程
So it picks up the environment from the place where that procedure was defined,
所以 它将环境从定义过程的地方取出
stores it in the procedure itself,
将它保存在过程自己内部
and then when the procedure is used,
之后当过程被调用时
the environment where it was defined is extended
它在被定义时的环境
with the new frame.
将由新的框架扩充
So this gives us a locus for putting where a variable has a value.
这给了我们一个放置有值的变量的地方
And, for example,
举个例子
if there are lots of guys pointing in at that environment,
如果有很多东西指向那这个环境
then they share that place.
它们就会共享这个环境
And we'll see more of that shortly.
我们很快将会见到
Well, now you have a new model
现在你们有了一个新模型
for understanding the execution of programs.
我们用它来理解程序的执行
I suppose I'll take questions now,
我觉得现在我应该解答一些问题了
and then we'll go on and use that for something.
之后我们再继续
AUDIENCE: Is it right to say then,
学生：这么说是对的吗？
the environment is that linked chain of frames starting with--
环境就是一些被连接在一起的框架
PROFESSOR: That's right.
教授：对
AUDIENCE:  working all the way back?
学生：通过它能够访问所有的框架？
PROFESSOR: Yes, the environment is a sequence of frames linked together.
教授：是的 环境是一系列被连接在一起的框架
And the way I like to think about it, it's the pointer to the first one,
我对它的理解是 它是指向第一个框架的指针
because once you've got that you've got them all.
因为一旦你获得了它 你就能拿到所有的框架
Anybody else?
还有谁有问题吗？
AUDIENCE: Is it possible to evaluate a procedure or to define a procedure in two different environments
学生：有可能在两个不同的环境中定义或求值一个过程
such that it will behave differently, and have pointers to both--
使得它有不同的行为 并且有指向两个环境的指针--
PROFESSOR: Oh, yes. The same procedure is not going to have two different environments.
教授：噢 是的 同一个过程不会有两个不同环境
The same code,
同样的代码
the same lambda expression
比如同样的LAMBDA表达式
can be evaluated in two environments producing two different procedures.
再不同的环境下求值可能产生不同的过程
Each procedure--
每个过程--
AUDIENCE: Their definition has the same name. Their operation--
学生：它们的定义有同样的名字 它们的运算--
PROFESSOR: The definition is written the same, with the same characters.
教授：它们定义是写起来是一样的 使用同样的字母
I can evaluate that set of characters,
我能求值那一组字母
whatever, that list structure that defines,
或定义的表结构之类的东西
that is the textual representation.
那只是文本表示
I can evaluate that in two different environments producing two different procedures.
我可以在两个不同环境种对它求值 产生两个不同的过程
Each of those procedures
每一个过程
has its own local sets of variables,
有它们自己的一组局部变量
and we'll see that right now.
我们很快就会看到
Anybody else?
还有问题吗？
OK, thank you. Let's take a break.
好 谢谢大家 我们休息一会
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
赋值、状态和副作用
Well, now I've done this terrible thing to you.
现在 我已经对你们做了一件非常糟糕的事儿
I've introduced a very complicated thing,
我引入了一个非常复杂的东西
assignment,
赋值
which destroys most of the interesting mathematical properties of our programs.
它摧毁了我们程序中大部分的 有趣的数学特性
Why should I have done this?
我为什么要做这件事呢
What possible good could this do?
这样做可能有什么好处吗？
Clearly not a nice thing,
很明显 这不是一个什么好东西
so I better have a good excuse.
因此我最好有一个好的理由
Well, let's do a little bit of playing,
让我们来小小地玩一下
first of all, with some very interesting programs that have assignment.
首先 我们写些非常有趣的带赋值的程序
Understand something special about them
来理解它们的特殊之处
that makes them somewhat valuable.
这些特殊之处使赋值变得有价值
Start with a very simple program
我们从一个非常简单的程序开始
I'm going to call make-counter.
我把这个程序叫做MAKE-COUNTER
I'm going to define make-counter
我要把它定义为
to be a procedure of one argument n
接受一个参数N的过程
which returns as its value a procedure of no arguments--
并且它的返回值是一个没有参数的过程--
a procedure that produces a procedure--
一个生成过程的过程--
which sets n to the increment of n
这个过程把N的值设为N+1
and returns that value of n.
并且返回N的值
Now we're going to investigate the behavior of this.
现在 我们要研究它的行为
It's a sort of interesting thing.
它很有趣
In order to investigate the behavior,
为了研究它的行为
I have to make an environment model,
我需要建立一个环境模型
because we can't understand this any other way.
因为我们不能通过其他的方式来理解它
So let's just do that.
所以我们开始吧
We start out with some sort of--
我们从这里开始
let's say there is a global environment that the machine is born with.
假设机器天生就有一个全局环境
Global we'll call it.
我们把它叫做Global
And it's going to have in it a bunch of initial things.
它内部有一堆初始化的东西
We all know what it's got.
我们都知道它里面有什么
It's got things in it like say, plus, and times,
这里面有+和*
and quotient, and difference, and CAR,
/ -和CAR
and etcetera,
以此类推
lots of things.
有很多东西
I don't know what they are,
我不知道它们是什么
some various squiggles
一些乱七八糟的符号
that are the things the machine is born with.
机器一开始就有这些特性
And by doing the definition here,
通过在这做定义
what I plan to do--
我要做的是--
Well, what am I doing?
我在干什么呢？
I'm doing this relative to the global environment.
我要把它关联到全局环境上
So here's my environment pointer.
这是我的环境指针
In order to do that I have to evaluate this lambda expression.
为了达到那个目的 我要求值这个LAMBDA表达式
That means I make a procedure object.
这意味着我创建了一个过程对象
So I'm going to make a procedure object here.
所以 我要在这创建一个过程对象
And the procedure object has,
这个过程对象
as the place it's defined,
由于在它被定义的地方
the global environment.
有一个全局的环境
The procedure object contains
这个过程对象包括了
some code that represents a procedure of one argument n
以N为参数的过程的代码
which returns a procedure of no arguments which does something.
它返回一个不接受参数的过程
And the define is a way of changing this environment,
DEFINE是一种改变环境的方法
so that I now add to it a make-counter,
所以我把MAKE-COUNTER加入全局环境中
a special rule for the special thing defined.
这是对于特殊的东西定义的一个特殊的规则
But what that is,
但它其实是
is it gives me that pointer to that procedure.
它给了我们一个指针 指向那个过程
So now the global environment contains make-counter as well.
所以现在全局环境中也有了MAKE-COUNTER
Now, we're going to do some operations.
现在 我们要进行一些操作
I'm going to use this to make some counters.
我要用它来创建一些计数器
We'll see what a counter is.
我们来看看计数器是什么
So let's define
所以我们定义
c1 to be a counter beginning at 0.
C1为一个从0开始的计数器
Well, we know how to do this now, according to the model.
根据模型 我们知道如何做这个了
I have to evaluate the expression make-counter in the global environment,
我需要在全局环境中求值这个表达式
make-counter of 0.
(MAKE-COUNTER 0)
Well, I look up make-counter and see that it's a procedure.
我查找MAKE-COUNTER 发现它是一个过程
I'm going to have to apply that procedure.
我将要应用这个过程
The way I apply the procedure
应用这个过程的方式
is by constructing a frame.
就是构建一个框架
Okay? So I construct a frame
所以我构建了一个框架
which has a value for n in it
它内部有一个N的值
which is 0
这个值是0
and the parent environment
它的父环境
is the one which is the environment of definition of make-counter.
就是定义MAKE-COUNTER时的环境
So I've made an environment by applying make-counter to 0.
所以我已经通过将MAKE-COUNTER应用于0上 而创建了一个环境
Now, I have to evaluate the body of make-counter,
现在 我需要求值MAKE-COUNTER的体
which is this lambda expression, in that environment.
就是那个环境中的LAMBDA表达式
Well evaluating this body,
求值这个体
this body is a lambda expression.
它是一个LAMBDA表达式
Evaluate a lambda expression means make a procedure object.
对LAMBDA表达式求值 意味着创建一个过程对象
So I'm going to make a procedure object.
所以我将创建一个过程对象
And that procedure object has
这个过程对象
the environment it was defined in being that,
拥有一个环境
where n was defined to be 0.
在这个环境中N被定义为0
And it has some code,
它有一些代码
which is the procedure of no arguments
这个过程不需要参数
which does something, then sets something,
该过程进行一些处理 然后进行赋值
and returns n.
并返回N
And this thing
这个东西
is going to be the object,
将成为一个对象
which in the global environment, will have the name c1.
在全局环境中 它的名字是C1
So we construct a name here, c1,
所以我们在这建立一个名字 C1
and say that equals that.
并且说C1等于这个过程
Now, but also make another counter,
现在 再来创建另一个计数器
c2 to be make-counter
通过MAKE-COUNTER创建c2
say, starting with 10.
让它从10开始
Then I do essentially the same thing.
然后我执行同样的步骤
I apply the make-counter procedure, which I got from here,
我应用这个MAKE-COUNTER过程
to make another frame with n being 10.
建立另一个框架 其中N等于10
That frame has the global environment as its parent.
全局环境作为它的父环境
I then construct a procedure
然后我构建一个过程
which has that as it's frame of definition.
以这个框架作为它定义的环境
The code of it is
它的代码是
the procedure of no arguments which does something.
完成一些操作的无参过程
And it does a set, and so on.
然后进行赋值 等等
And n comes out. Okay?
然后返回N
And c2 is this.
这就是C2
Well, you're already beginning to see something fairly interesting.
好 你们应该发现 某些东西开始变得有趣了
There are two n's here.
这里有两个N
They are not one n.
它们不是同一个N
Each time I called make-counter,
我每次调用MAKE-COUNTER的时候
I made another instance of n.
我就创建了另一个N的实例
These are distinct and separate from each other.
它们彼此独立 没有关联
Now, let's do some execution, use those counters.
现在 我们来使用一下这些计数器
Well, what happens if I say, c1 at this point?
如果此时 我调用C1 会发生什么？
Well, I go over here,
我会在这里查找
and I say, oh yes, c1 is a procedure.
发现C1是一个过程
I'm going to call this procedure on no arguments,
我要不带参数地调用这个过程
but it has no parameters.
因为它不需要参数
That's right.
对吧？
What's its body?
它的体是什么呢？
Well, I have to look over here, because I didn't write it down.
我得来这里解释 因为我没有给誊过来
It said, set n to one plus n
这个过程体是将N赋值为N+1
and return n,
并且返回N
increment n.
就是把N增大1
Well, the n it says is this one.
它的N指的是这个
So I increment that n.
所以我把这个n增大1
That becomes one,
它变成了1
and I return the value one.
然后返回了1
Supposing I then called c2.
之后我调用C2
Well, what do I do?
我会做什么？
I say c2 is this procedure which does the same thing,
C2是相同的过程
but here's the n.
但这个N
It becomes 11.
它变成了11
And so I have an 11 which is the value.
所以返回值是11
I then can say, let's try c1 again.
然后我们再来调用一下C1
hum, c1 is this,
C1是这个
that's two,
它是2
so the answer is two.
所以结果是2
And c2
然后调用C2
gives me a 12 by the same method,
然后C2通过同样的方法 返回了12
by walking down here looking at that
它在这里进行查找
and saying, here's the n, I'm incrementing.
发现了N 并把它加1
So what I have are computational objects.
我拥有的是可计算的对象
There are two counters,
它们是两个计数器
each with its own independent local state.
每一个都有各自独立的局部状态
Let's talk about this a little.
我们再进一步
This is a strange thing.
这是个奇怪的东西
What's an object?
什么是对象？
It's not at all obvious what an object is.
这个概念并不明确
We like to think about objects,
我们倾向于以对象的角度思考
because it's economical to think that way.
因为这样思考比较经济
It's an intellectual economy.
这是一种智力上的经济
I am an object.
我是一个对象
You are an object.
你也是一个对象
We are not the same object.
但我们不是同一个对象
I can divide the world into two parts,
我可以把世界分为两部分
me and you,
我和你
and there's other things as well,
以及其它的东西
such that
使得
most of the things I might want to discuss about my workings
大多数对于我的讨论
do not involve you,
不会影响到你
and most of the things I want to discuss about your workings don't involve me.
大多数对于你的讨论不会牵涉到我
I have a blood pressure,
我有血压
a temperature,
体温
a respiration rate,
呼吸频率
certain amount of sugar in my blood,
血液中有确定的血糖值
and numerous, thousands, of state variables-- millions actually,
数不清的 数以千计的状态变量--上百万实际上
or I don't know how many--
我不知道具体有多少
huge numbers of state variables in the physical sense
以物理学观点 我拥有大量的状态变量
which represent the state of me as a particle,
如果将我视为一个粒子的话
and you have gazillions of them as well.
你也有许许多多这样的变量
And most of mine are uncoupled to most of yours.
我们的大多数变量之间是好无联系的
So we can compute the properties of me
所以可以计算我的属性
without worrying too much about the properties of you.
而不用太担心你的属性
If we had to work about both of us together,
如果把我们两个放在一起计算
than the number of states that we have to consider
那么我们需要考虑的状态的数量
is the product of the number of states you have and the number of states I have.
就是你与我的状态的数量的乘积
But this way it's almost a sum.
按对象解耦的话 则只需考虑你我状态之和
Now, indeed there are forces that couple us.
然而 实际上有一种力量把我们耦合起来
I'm talking to you and your state changes.
我对你讲话 你的状态就变了
I'm looking at you and my state changes.
我看着你 我的状态就变了
Some of my state variables, a very few of them,
因此 我的变量中的一小部分
therefore, are coupled to yours.
与你的一些变量是耦合的
If you were to suddenly yell very loud,
如果你突然大喊大叫
my blood pressure would go up.
我的血压就会升高
However, and it may not be always appropriate
然而 将世界看作是由独立的变量
to think about the world as being made out of independent states and independent particles.
和独立的粒子组成的是不恰当的
Lots of the bugs that occur in things like quantum mechanics,
在像量子力学这样的东西里存在大量的BUG
or the bugs in our minds that occur when we think about things like quantum mechanics,
或者当我们思考像量子力学之类的东西的时候 会在我们的脑海中产生bug
are due the fact that we are trying to think about things
这是由于 当我们思考事物时
being broken up into independent pieces,
会去将事物分解为相互独立的部分来看待
when in fact there's more coupling than we see on the surface,
而事实上事物的耦合程度 远远大于在表面所看到的
or that we want to believe in,
即便这样 我们仍像那样思考
because we want to compute efficiently and effectively.
是因为我们希望高效并且有效的进行计算
We've been trained to think that way.
我们被培养成以那种方式进行思考
Well, let's see.
大家看
How would we know if we had objects at all?
我们如何才能知道我们是否有对象？
How can we tell if we have objects?
如果我们有对象 应该如何分辨呢？
Consider some possible optical illusions.
通过思考一些光学现象
This could be done.
就能解答这个问题
These pieces of chalk are not appropriately identical,
这几截粉笔不完全相同
but supposing you couldn't tell the difference of them by looking at them.
但假设 只通过观察是无法区分它们的
Well, there's a possibility
有一种可能
that this all a game I'm playing with mirrors.
是这一切都是我们与镜子的游戏
It's really the same piece of chalk,
它们真的是同一截粉笔
but you're seeing two of them.
但你看到了两个
How would you know if you're seeing one or two?
你怎么知道你看到的是一个还是两个呢？
Well, there's only one way I know.
我只知道有一种方法可以确定
You grab one of them and change it
抓起其中一个并且改变它
and see if the other one changed.
然后看看另一个有没有跟着变化
And it didn't,
而另一个没有变化
so there's two of them.
所以它们是两截不同粉笔
And, on the other hand,
另一方面
there is some other screwy properties of things like that.
事物还有一些其它的类似的纠结属性
Like, how do we know if something changed?
例如 我们怎么才知道某个东西是否改变了呢？
We have to look at it before and after the change.
我们需要在它改变之前和之后进行观察
The change is an assignment,
改变就是赋值
it's a moment in time.
它是时间中的一个时刻
But that means we have to know it was the same one that we're looking at.
但是那意味着我们需要知道 我们看到的是否是同一个
So some very strange, and unusual,
所以一些东西非常奇怪
and obscure, and -- I don't understand
不同寻常并且晦涩难懂
the problems associated with assignment,
并且我不理解与赋值
and change, and objects.
变化以及对象有关的问题
These could get very, very bad.
这些东西可能变得非常非常糟糕
For example,
例如
here I am, I am a particular person,
我 一个特定的人
a particular object, okay?
一个特定的对象
Now, I can take out my knife,
现在 我可以拿出小刀
and cut my fingernail.
切下一片我的指甲
Alright? A piece of my fingernail has fallen off onto the table.
一片指甲掉在了桌子上
I believe I am the same person I was a second ago,
我相信自己和一秒钟之前的自己 是同一个人
but I'm not physically the same in the slightest.
但在物理上并不是分毫不差
I have changed.
我已经改变了
Why am I the same?
为什么我还是同一个人呢？
What is the identity of me?
什么能认定我的身份呢？
I don't know...Okay?
我不知道
Except for the fact that I have some sort of identity.
除非我有某种特征
And so, I think by introducing assignment and objects,
我觉得 由于引入赋值和对象
we have opened ourselves up to all the horrible questions of philosophy
我们不得不去面对这种
that have been plaguing philosophers for some thousands of years about this sort of thing.
困扰了哲学家们上千年的哲学问题
It's why mathematics is a lot cleaner.
这也是相比之下 为什么数学清晰得多
Let's look at the best things I know to say about actions and identity.
我将尽我所能地向大家阐述关于动作和身份的理解
We say that an action, a, had an effect on an object, x,
我们说动作A 对于对于某个对象X有影响
or equivalently,
换句话说
that x was changed by a,
X被A改变
if some property, p, which was true of x before a,
如果某个属性P 在P作用于X之前为真
became false of x after a.
在A作用于X之后为假
That's test.
那是个测试
It still means I have to have the x before and after.
这也意味着 我必须有变动前和变动后的X
Or, the other way of saying this is,
或者 换句话说
we say that two objects x and y are the same for any action
我们说对任一动作 两个对象X和Y是同一个对象
which has an effect on x has the same effect on y
当且仅当 该动作对X、Y有同样的影响
However, objects are very useful,
然而 就像我说的
as I said, for intellectual economy.
对象在智力经济上是非常有用的
One of the things that's incredibly useful about them,
对于它们来说非常有用的东西之一
is that the world
就是对于这个世界
is made out of independent objects with independent local state.
我们习惯于把它认为是由带有独立状态的独立对象所构成的
We like to think that way, although it isn't completely true.
虽然那并不完全正确 但我们喜欢以那样的的方式来思考
When we want to make very complicated programs
当我们要写一个非常复杂的程序
that deal with such a world,
来应对这样一个世界时
if we want those programs to be understandable by us
如果我们希望这些程序可以被我们理解
and also to be changeable,
并且也是可修改的
so that if we change the world we change the program only a little bit,
那么如果世界改变了 我们只需要稍微改动一下程序
then we want there to be connections, isomorphism,
我们希望建立一种联系 一种同构
between the objects in the world and the objects in our mental model.
建立在真实世界的对象与我们脑海中的对象之间
The modularity of the world can give us the modularity in our programming.
世界的模块化 使我们的程序得以模块化
So we invent things called object-oriented programming and things like that
所以我们发明了面向对象编程
to provide us with that power.
使我们获得那样的力量
But it's even easier.
但是 它甚至更简单
Let's play a little game.
让我们玩一个小游戏
I want to play a little game,
我想通过这个游戏
show you an even easier example
给你展示一个更简单的例子
or where modularity can be enhanced by using an assignment statement, judiciously.
来说明谨慎地使用赋值语句 可以增强模块性
One thing I want to enforce and impress on you,
有一件事 我想让你牢牢地铭记
is don't use assignment statements the way
就是不要像在FORTRAN Basic
you use it in FORTRAN or Basic or something or Pascal,
或者Pascal里一样使用赋值语句
to do the things you don't have to do with it.
你不那样做 也能达到目的
It's not the right way to think for most things.
这不是思考大多数事情的正确方式
Sometimes it's essential,
有些时候它是必要的
or maybe it's essential.
或者可能是必要的
We'll see more about that too.
我们一会更深入地去研究
OK, let me show you a fun game here.
我要给你展示一个有趣的游戏
There was a mathematician
从前有一个数学家
by the name of Cesaro--or Cesaro, Cesaro I suppose it is--
叫做Cesaro
who figured out a clever way of computing pi.
他发现了一个计算pi的巧妙方法
It turns out that if I take two random numbers
这个方法是说 如果我有两个随机数
two integers at random,
两个随机的整数
and compute the greatest common divisor,
计算它们的最大公约数
their greatest common divisor is either one or it's not one.
结果可能是1 或者不是1
If it's one, then they have no common divisors.
如果是1 它们没有公约数
If their greatest common divisor is one--
如果它们的最大公约数是1
the probability that two random numbers,
这两个随机数
two numbers chosen at random, has as greatest common divisor one
两个随机生成的数 最大公约数为1的概率
is related to pi.
与pi有关系
In fact--
事实上
yes, it's very strange--
是的 这很奇怪
of course there are other ways of computing pi,
当然有其他计算pi的方法
like dropping pins on flags, and things like that, and sort of the same kind of thing.
像投针法之类的的方法
So the probability of that the GCD of number one and number two,
N1和N2的最大公约数是1的概率为
two random numbers chosen,
N1、N2是随机选取的两个数
is 6 over pi squared.
是6/pi^2
I'm not going to try to prove that.
我不准备证明这个
It's actually not too hard and sort of fun.
事实上这不难 并且有些有趣
How would we estimate such probability?
我们要怎样估算这个概率呢？
Well, the way we do that, the way we estimate the probabilities,
我们估算概率的方法则是
is by doing lots of experiments,
是做大量的实验
and then computing the ratios of the ones that come out one way
去计算成功的试验
to the total number of experiments we do.
与试验总次数的比率
It's called Monte Carlo,
这种方法叫做蒙特卡罗方法
and it's useful in other contexts for doing things like integrals where you have lots and lots of variables--
它也可以用于计算包含大量变量的积分
the space which is limiting the dimensions you are doing you integral in.
其中积分的面积是限定的
But going back to here,
回到这里
Let's look at this slide,
我们来看看这张幻灯片
We can use Cesaro's method for estimating pi
我们可以用Cesaro的方法来估算pi的值
with n trials by taking the square root of six over a Monte Carlo,
通过N次试验 取结果的六分之一 开根号
a Monte Carlo experiment with n trials,
用蒙特卡罗方法
with n trials using Cesaro's experiment,
进行了N次Cesaro实验
where Cesaro's experiment is the test of whether the GCD of two random numbers--
这个实验是关于两个随机数的最大公约数的--
And you can see that I've already got some assignments in here,
你可以看到 我已经在这里进行了一些赋值
just by what I wrote.
就像我写的这样
The fact that this word rand, in parentheses,
这个在括号中的RAND
therefore, that procedure call,
这个过程调用
yields a different value than this one,
生成了一个与这个RAND不同的值
at least that's what I'm assuming by writing this this way,
至少是我写的这样所假设的
indicates that this is not a function,
这表明这不是一个函数
that there's internal state in it which is changing.
这里面会有一个不断改变内部状态
If the GCD of those two random numbers is equal to one,
如果两个随机数的最大公约数等于1
that's the experiment.
这就是整个实验过程
So here I have an experimental method for estimating the value of pi.
那么我有了一个实验方法 用来估算pi的值
Where, I can easily divide this problem into two parts.
我可以轻松地将这个问题分为两个部分
One is the specific Monte Carlo experiment of Cesaro, which you just saw,
一部分是使用蒙特卡罗方法进行特定的Cesaro实验 就像你刚才看到那个
and the other is the general technique of doing Monte Carlo experiments.
另一部分就是一般性蒙特卡罗方法的实现
And that's what this is.
就是这个
If I want to do Monte Carlo experiments with n trials,
如果我想进行N次蒙特卡罗试验
a certain number of trials, and a particular experiment,
即一个确定的试验次数 和一个确定的实验
the way I do that
我进行实验的方法就是
is I make a little iterative procedure
构建一个迭代过程
which has variable the number of trials remaining and the number trials that have been passed,
这个过程有两个变量 分别是试验的剩余次数和通过次数
that I've gotten true.
也就是实验结果为真的次数
And if the number remaining is 0,
如果剩余次数为0
then the answer is the number past divided by this whole number of trials,
结果就是通过的次数除以总次数
was the estimate of the probability.
也就是该概率的估算值
And if it's not,
如果剩余次数不是0
if I have more trials to do,
如果还有试验要做
then let's do one. We do an experiment.
那么接下来我们就进行一次试验
We call the procedure which is experiment on no arguments.
我们调用一次没有参数的实验的过程
We do the experiment
我们进行这个试验
and then, if that turned out to be true,
如果实验结果为真
we go around the loop
我们继续循环
decrementing the number of experiments we have to do by one
试验剩余次数减1
and incrementing the number that were passed.
将试验通过次数加1
And if the experiment was false,
如果试验的结果为假
we just go around the loop
我们继续循环
decrementing the number of experiments remaining
剩余试验次数减1
and keeping the number passed the same.
试验通过次数保持不变
We start this up iterating over the total number of trials with 0 experiments past.
我们以TRIAL为剩余次数 以0为通过次数 开始迭代
A very elegant little program.
多么简洁的小程序啊
And I don't have to just do this with Cesaro's experiment,
我不一定非要进行Cesaro的实验
it could be lots of Monte Carlo experiments I might do.
它可以用来进行很多种蒙特卡罗实验
Of course, this depends upon the existence of some sort of random number generator.
当然 它依赖于某种随机数生成器的存在
And random number generators generally look something like this.
随机数生成器通常是像这种的东西
There is a random number generator--
这是一个随机数生成器--
is in fact a procedure which is going to do something just like the counter.
它实际上就是一个过程 具体行为跟计数器有些相似
It's going to update an x
它会把X的值更新为
to the result of applying some function to x,
将某个函数应用于X的结果
where this function is some screwy kind of function
而这类古怪的函数
that you might find out in Knuth's books on the details of programming.
你可以在Kunth写的关于编程细节的书中找到
He does these wonderful books that are full of the details of programming,
他写的书绝妙而充满了编程细节
because I can't remember how to make a random number generator,
虽然我记不住随机数生成器该怎样写
but I can look it up there, and I can find out.
但我可以在书里找出一个来用
And then, eventually, I return the value of x
最后 我返回了X的值
which is the state variable internal to the random number generator.
也就是随机数生成器的内部状态变量
That state variable is initialized somehow,
这个状态变量以某种方式被初始化
and has a value.
从而获得了一个值
And this procedure is defined in the context where that variable is bound
这个过程被定义在那个变量被约束的上下文中
So this is a hidden piece of local state that you see here.
所以你在这看到的 是一个隐藏的局部状态
And this procedure is defined in that context.
这个过程定义在那个上下文中
Now, that's a very simple thing to do.
这样做起来非常容易
And it's very nice.
而且结果也非常好
Supposing, I didn't want to use assignments.
设想 我不想用赋值
Supposing, I wanted to write this program without assignments.
假设我想写一个不带赋值的程序
What problems would I have?
我将遇到什么困难？
Well, let's see.
让我们来看看
I'd like to use the overhead machine here,
我要用一下头顶上的投影仪了
thank you.
多谢
First of all, let's look at the whole thing. It's a big story. Right?
首先 我们来整体看一下 这是一个很庞大的东西
Unfortunately, which tells you there is something wrong.
它告诉你有某些东西出了问题
It's at least that big,
毕竟有这么大一堆东西呢
and it's monolithic.
庞大而单一
You don't have to understand or look at the text there right now
你不需要现在去理解或看这里的文本
to see that it's monolithic.
就把它们看做一个整体
It isn't a thing which is Cesaro's experiment.
它不是Cesaro的实验
It's not pulled out from the Monte Carlo process.
它不是从蒙特卡罗过程中抽取出来的
It's not separated. Let's look why.
它不是分离的 让我们来看看为什么
Remember, the constraint here
记住 这里的约束是
is that every procedure
每个过程
return the same value for the same arguments.
对于同样的参数 将返回同样的值
Every procedure represents a function.
每个过程就是一个函数
That's a different kind of constraint.
那是另一种约束
Because when I have assignments, I can  change some internal state variable.
因为当我赋值时 我可以改变一些内部状态变量
So let's see how that causes things to go wrong.
所以让我们来看看它是怎么出错的
Well, start at the beginning.
我们从头开始
Ah...The estimate of pi looks sort of the same.
估算pi的过程看起来是一样的
What I'm doing is I take the square root
我取RAMDOM-GCD-TEST应用于N
of six over the random GCD test applied to n
的结果分之6的平方根
whereas that's what this is.
就是这个
But here, we are beginning to see something funny.
在这里 我们开始看到了一些有趣的东西
The random GCD test of a certain number of trials
对于以TRAILS为参数的RANDOM-GCD-TEST过程
is just like we had before,
就像我们之前做的一样
an iteration on the number of trials remaining,
是一个以剩余次数
the number of trials that have been passed,
通过次数
and another variable x.
另一个变量X为基准的迭代
What's that x?
这个X是什么？
That x is the state of the random number generator.
X是随机数发生器的状态
And it is now going to be used here.
它会在这里被使用
The same random update function that I have over here
这里的同样的随机更新函数
is the one I would have used in a random number generator if I were building it the other way,
来自于一个我另外写的随机数发生器
the one I get out of Knuth's books.
或者从Knuth的书中找一个
x is going to get transformed into x1,
X将转化为X1
I need two random numbers.
但我需要两个随机数
And x1 is going to get transformed into x2,
X1将被转化为X2
I have two random numbers.
我有两个随机数
I then have to do exactly what I did before.
然后进行和之前一样的步骤
I take the GCD of x1 x2.
取X1和X2的最大公约数
If that's one, then I go around the loop with X2 being the next value of x.
如果结果是1 则将X2作为下一个X的值继续循环
You see what's happened here
这里所发生的
is that the state of the random number generator
随机数发生器的状态
is no longer confined to the insides of the random number generator.
不再被限制于其内部
It has leaked out.
它已经暴露了出来
It has leaked out into my procedure
它已经被暴露在
that does the Monte Carlo experiment.
我们的的蒙特卡罗实验的过程中
But what's worse than that,
但比那更糟糕的是
is it's also, because it was contained inside my experiment itself, Cesaro,
同样的 因为它也被包含在我们的Cesaro实验中
It leaked out that two. Because Cesaro called twice,
它被暴露了两次 因为Cesaro被调用了两次
has to have a different value each time,
每次有不同的值
if I going to have a legitimate experimental test.
如果我要进行一个合理的实验的话
So Cesaro can't be a function either,
所以Cesaro也不能成为函数了
unless I pass it the seed of the random number generator that is going to go wandering around.
除非我把随机数发生器的种子传给它
So unfortunately, the seed of random number generator
所以很不幸 随机数发生器的种子
has leaked out into Cesaro, from the random number generator,
从随机数发生器中暴露到了Cesaro内部
that's leaked into the Monte Carlo experiment.
被暴露在蒙特卡罗实验中
And, unfortunately, my Monte Carlo experiment here is no longer general.
很不幸 这里的蒙特卡罗实验不再是通用的了
The Monte Carlo experiment here
这里的蒙特卡罗实验
knows how many random numbers I need to do the experiment.
知道了我在实验中需要多少个随机数
That's sort of horrible.
这真的很糟糕
I lost an ability to decompose a problem into pieces,
我失去了将问题分解开来的能力
because I wasn't willing to accept the little loop of information,
因为我不愿意接受信息的循环
the feedback process,
反馈的过程
that happens inside the random number generator before
这之前都是发生在随机数发生器内部
that was made by having an assignment to a state variable that was confined to the random number generator.
也就是赋值给一个限制在随机数生成器内部的状态变量
So the fact that the random number generator is an object,
所以实际上 随机数发生器是一个对象
with an internal state variable,
它有一个内部状态变量
it's affected by nothing,
它不受任何东西影响
but it'll give you something, and it will apply it's force to you,
但是它会给你某些东西 把它的力量赐予你
that was what we're missing now.
那是我们现在缺少的
OK, well I think we've seen
好 我认为我已经知道了
enough reason for doing this,
引入赋值的充分理由
and it all sort of looks very wonderful.
并且一些看起来很圆满
Wouldn't it be nice if assignment was a good thing
如果赋值是一个好东西
and maybe it's worth it,
并且赋值是值得的 这不是很好吗？
but I'm not sure.
我不是很确定
As Mr. Gilbert and Sullivan said,
Mr. Gilbert和Sullivan说过
things are seldom what they seem,
事物往往不像表面看到的那样
skim milk masquerades as cream.
脱脂牛奶也能装成奶油
Are there any questions?
谁有什么问题吗？
Are there any philosophers here?
在座的有哲学家吗？
Anybody want to argue about objects?
有人想要讨论有关“对象”的问题吗？
You're just floored, right?
你们已经一头雾水了是吧？
And you haven't done your homework yet.
你们还没有完成家庭作业呢
You haven't come up with a good question.
你们需要提一个好问题
Oh, well.
好了
Sure, thank you. Let's take the long break now.
感谢你们 我们下课吧
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP